A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director/President, SG 1, Series 31 FA303
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director/President, SG 1, Series 31
1919-1985, 1987-1995
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harkness, Anna M. Richardson
Harkness, Edward Stephen
Commonwealth Fund
Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman
Harkness, Charles W.
FA303
17.04 Cubic Feet 36 document boxes and 1 record storage box.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accession 1986:069, and several subsequent additions.
Scope and Contents
Barry C. Smith served as General Director of the Commonwealth Fund, 1920-1947. During this period the reports were officially titled as Report of the General Director to the Directors of the Commonwealth Fund. Beginning in 1948, the offical title became known as Report of the President and Staff to Directors of the Commonwealth Fund.
Conditions Governing Access note
Reports of the General Director/President are open for scholarly research.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Select records, as noted, are closed to scholarly research due to preservation concerns.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports, SG 1, Series 4
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library, SG 1, Series 5
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program, SG 1, Series 6
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors, SG 1, Series 7
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants, SG 1, Series 8
FA281 Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics, SG 1, Series 10
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies, SG 1, Series 11
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health, SG 1, Series 12
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications, SG 1, Series 13
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals, SG 1, Series 14
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research, SG 1, Series 15
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 16
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee, SG 1, Series 17
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants, SG 1, Series 18
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family, SG 1, Series 19
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, SG 1, Series 20
FA428 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships, Fellows Reports, SG 1, Series 20A
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance, SG 1, Series 21
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program, SG 1, Series 22
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program, SG 1, Series 23
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program, SG 1, Series 24
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program, SG 1, Series 25
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust, SG 1, Series 28
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency, SG 1, Series 29
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files, SG 1, Series 30
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director, SG 1, Series 31
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer, SG 1, Series 32
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists, SG 1, Series 33 - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz), SG 1, Series 34 - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials, SG 1, Series 35
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files, SG 1, Series 1
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files, SG 1, Series 2
FA429 Commonwealth Fund records, President, Margaret E. Mahoney, SG 2, Series 1
FA430 Commonwealth Fund records, Book Program, SG 2, Series 2
Legal issues; Law; Medical education; Legal research; Child welfare; Child psychology; Hygiene; Education, Rural; Medicine, Rural; Medical research; Mental health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Public health; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Child mental health; War relief; United States; Public welfare; Yale University; Phillips Exeter Academy; Harkness, Anna M. Richardson; Harkness, Edward Stephen; Commonwealth Fund; Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman; Columbia University; Harkness, Charles W.; Harvard University; Social Science Research Council
- 1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1921 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 1922 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- 1923 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- 1924 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 1925 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- 1926 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- 1927 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- 1928 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- 1929 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- 1930-1931 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- 1932-1933 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- 1936-1937 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- 1938-1939 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- 1919 March 6 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- 1919 April 1 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- 1919 May 6 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- 1919 June 3 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- 1919 June 19 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- 1919 September 30 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- 1919 November 13 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- 1919 December 13 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- 1920 January 20 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- 1920 February 17 (Box 8, Folder 26)
- 1920 April 8 (Box 8, Folder 27)
- 1920 May 6 (Box 8, Folder 28)
- 1920 June 26 (Box 8, Folder 29)
- 1920 October 5 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- 1920 November 30 (Box 9, Folder 31)
- 1921 January 11 (Box 9, Folder 32)
- 1921 February 1 (Box 9, Folder 33)
- 1921 March (Box 9, Folder 34)
- 1921 May 6 (Box 9, Folder 35)
- 1921 May 24 (Box 9, Folder 36)
- 1921 June 25 (Box 9, Folder 37)
- 1921 November 9 (Box 9, Folder 38)
- 1921 December 6 (Box 9, Folder 39)
- 1922 January 17 (Box 9, Folder 40)
- 1922 February 16 (Box 9, Folder 41)
- 1922 April 4 (Box 9, Folder 42)
- 1922 May 9 (Box 9, Folder 43)
- 1922 June 7 (Box 10, Folder 44)
- 1922 November (Box 10, Folder 45)
- 1922 December 12 (Box 10, Folder 46)
- 1923 January 16 (Box 10, Folder 47)
- 1923 February (Box 10, Folder 48)
- 1923 March 13 (Box 10, Folder 49)
- 1923 May 15 (Box 10, Folder 50)
- 1923 June 5 (Box 10, Folder 51)
- 1923 October 23 (Box 10, Folder 52)
- 1923 December 4 (Box 10, Folder 53)
- 1924 February 5 (Box 10, Folder 54)
- 1924 April 8 (Box 10, Folder 55)
- 1924 May 23 (Box 11, Folder 56)
- 1924 June (Box 11, Folder 57)
- 1924 November 11 (Box 11, Folder 58)
- 1924 December 9 (Box 11, Folder 59)
- 1925 February 3 (Box 11, Folder 60)
- 1925 April 22 (Box 11, Folder 61)
- 1925 June 3 (Box 11, Folder 62)
- 1925 November 4 (Box 11, Folder 63)
- 1925 December 8 (Box 11, Folder 64)
- 1926 January 6 (Box 11, Folder 65)
- 1926 April (Box 11, Folder 66)
- 1926 June (Box 11, Folder 67)
- 1926 October 20 (Box 11, Folder 68)
- 1926 December 16 (Box 12, Folder 69)
- 1927 February 8 (Box 12, Folder 70)
- 1927 March 30 (Box 12, Folder 71)
- 1927 June 8 (Box 12, Folder 72)
- 1927 October 5 (Box 12, Folder 73)
- 1927 December 20 (Box 12, Folder 74)
- 1928 February 28 (Box 12, Folder 75)
- 1928 June 5 (Box 12, Folder 76)
- 1928 October 9 (Box 12, Folder 77)
- 1928 December 18 (Box 12, Folder 78)
- 1929 February 14 (Box 12, Folder 79)
- 1929 June 5 (Box 13, Folder 80)
- 1929 July 26 (Box 13, Folder 81)
- 1929 October 30 (Box 13, Folder 82)
- 1929 December 18 (Box 13, Folder 83)
- 1930 April 9 (Box 13, Folder 84)
- 1930 June 10 (Box 13, Folder 85)
- 1930 October 7 (Box 13, Folder 86)
- 1930 December 16 (Box 13, Folder 87)
- 1931 April 7 (Box 13, Folder 88)
- 1931 June 9 (Box 13, Folder 89)
- 1931 October 13 (Box 13, Folder 90)
- 1931 December 15 (Box 13, Folder 91)
- 1932 April 5 (Box 14, Folder 92)
- 1932 June 14 (Box 14, Folder 93)
- 1932 October 4 (Box 14, Folder 94)
- 1932 December 13 (Box 14, Folder 95)
- 1933 April 18 (Box 14, Folder 96)
- 1933 June 13 (Box 14, Folder 97)
- 1933 October 17 (Box 14, Folder 98)
- 1933 December 12 (Box 14, Folder 99)
- 1934 April 24 (Box 14, Folder 100)
- 1934 June 12 (Box 14, Folder 101)
- 1934 October 2 (Box 14, Folder 102)
- 1934 December 11 (Box 14, Folder 103)
- 1935 April 16 (Box 14, Folder 104)
- 1935 June 11 (Box 14, Folder 105)
- 1935 October 15 (Box 14, Folder 106)
- 1935 December 17 (Box 14, Folder 107)
- 1936 April 21 (Box 14, Folder 108)
- 1936 June 9 (Box 14, Folder 109)
- 1936 October 13 (Box 15, Folder 110)
- 1936 December 15 (Box 15, Folder 111)
- 1937 April 8 (Box 15, Folder 112)
- 1937 June (Box 15, Folder 113)
- 1937 October (Box 15, Folder 114)
- 1937 December 16 (Box 15, Folder 115)
- 1938 April 21 (Box 15, Folder 116)
- 1938 June 16 (Box 15, Folder 117)
- 1938 October 13 (Box 15, Folder 118)
- 1938 December 15 (Box 15, Folder 119)
- 1939 April 20 (Box 15, Folder 120)
- 1939 June 15 (Box 15, Folder 121)
- 1939 October 11 (Box 15, Folder 122)
- 1939 December 14 (Box 15, Folder 123)
- 1940 April 25 (Box 16, Folder 124)
- 1940 June 13 (Box 16, Folder 125)
- 1940 October 17 (Box 16, Folder 126)
- 1940 December 12 (Box 16, Folder 127)
- 1941 April 10 (Box 16, Folder 128)
- 1941 June 12 (Box 16, Folder 129)
- 1941 October 9 (Box 16, Folder 130)
- 1941 December 18 (Box 16, Folder 131)
- 1942 April 9 (Box 16, Folder 132)
- 1942 June 11 (Box 16, Folder 133)
- 1942 October 15 (Box 16, Folder 134)
- 1942 December 17 (Box 16, Folder 135)
- 1943 April 8 (Box 16, Folder 136)
- 1943 June 10 (Box 17, Folder 137)
- 1943 October 22 (Box 17, Folder 138)
- 1943 December 16 (Box 17, Folder 139)
- 1944 April 14 (Box 17, Folder 140)
- 1944 June 16 (Box 17, Folder 141)
- 1944 October 20 (Box 17, Folder 142)
- 1944 December 14 (Box 17, Folder 143)
- 1945 April 6 (Box 17, Folder 144)
- 1945 June 14 (Box 17, Folder 145)
- 1945 October 11 (Box 17, Folder 146)
- 1945 December 14 (Box 17, Folder 147)
- 1946 March 29 (Box 17, Folder 148)
- 1946 June 20 (Box 17, Folder 149)
- 1946 October 18 (Box 17, Folder 150)
- 1946 December 13 (Box 17, Folder 151)
- 1947 April 18
  Conditions Governing Access
  Closed to scholarly research due to preservation concerns.
- 1947 June 12
- 1947 December 11
- 1948 March
- 1948 April 8
- 1948 April 9
- 1948 June 10
- 1948 October 14
- 1949 April 21
- 1949 June 16
- 1949 October 10
- 1949 October 27
- 1950 January 19
- 1950 April 13
- 1950 June 8
- 1950 June
- 1950 October 19
- 1951 January 11
- 1951 June 14
- 1951 October 11
- 1952 January 11
- 1952 May 9
- 1952 November 20
- 1952
- 1952 November 20 (Box 18, Folder 152)
- 1953 February 20 (Box 18, Folder 153)
- 1953 May 15 (Box 18, Folder 154)
- 1953 November 12 (Box 18, Folder 155)
- 1954 February 25 (Box 18, Folder 156)
- 1954 May 13 (Box 18, Box 157)
- 1954 November 18 (Box 18, Folder 158)
- 1955 February 10 (Box 18, Folder 159)
- 1955 May 26 (Box 18, Folder 160)
- 1955 November 17 (Box 18, Folder 161)
- 1956 February 9 (Box 18, Folder 162)
- 1956 May 17 (Box 19, Folder 163)
- 1956 November 15 (Box 19, Folder 164)
- 1957 February 14 (Box 19, Folder 165)
- 1957 May 16 (Box 19, Folder 166)
- 1957 November 14 (Box 19, Folder 167)
- 1958 February 13 (Box 19, Folder 168)
- 1958 May 8 (Box 19, Folder 169)
- 1958 November 13 (Box 19, Folder 170)
- 1959 February 11 (Box 19, Folder 171)
- 1959 May 21 (Box 20, Folder 172)
- 1959 November 12 (Box 20, Folder 173)
- 1960 February 11 (Box 20, Folder 174)
- 1960 May 12 (Box 20, Folder 175)
- 1960 November 10 (Box 20, Folder 176)
- 1961 February 9 (Box 20, Folder 177)
- 1961 May 11 (Box 20, Folder 178)
- 1961 November 9 (Box 20, Folder 179)
- 1962 February 8 (Box 20, Folder 180)
- 1962 May 10 (Box 20, Folder 181)
- 1962 November 8 (Box 20, Folder 182)
- 1963 February 14 (Box 21, Folder 183)
- 1963 May 9 (Box 21, Folder 184)
- 1963 November 14 (Box 21, Folder 185)
- 1964 February 13 (Box 21, Folder 186)
- 1964 May 14 (Box 21, Folder 187)
- 1964 November 12 (Box 21, Folder 188)
- 1965 February 25 (Box 21, Folder 189)
- 1965 May 13 (Box 21, Folder 190)
- 1965 November 10 (Box 21, Folder 191)
- 1966 February 10 (Box 21, Folder 192)
- 1966 May 12 (Box 21, Folder 193)
- 1966 November 3 (Box 22, Folder 194)
- 1967 February 7 (Box 22, Folder 195)
- 1967 May 11 (Box 22, Folder 196)
- 1967 November 9 (Box 22, Folder 197)
- 1968 February 15 (Box 22, Folder 198)
- 1968 May 9 (Box 22, Folder 199)
- 1968 November 14 (Box 22, Folder 200)
- 1969 February 13 (Box 22, Folder 201)
- 1969 May 26 (Box 22, Folder 202)
- 1969 November 13 (Box 23, Folder 203)
- 1970 February 19 (Box 23, Folder 204)
- 1970 May 26 (Box 23, Folder 205)
- 1970 November 12 (Box 23, Folder 206)
- 1971 February 24 (Box 23, Folder 207)
- 1971 April 14 (Box 23, Folder 208)
- 1971 May 25 (Box 23, Folder 209)
- 1971 November 10 (Box 23, Folder 210)
- 1972 February 9 (Box 23, Folder 211)
- 1972 May 11 (Box 23, Folder 212)
- 1972 November 9 (Box 24, Folder 213)
- 1973 February 8 (Box 24, Folder 214)
- 1973 May 17 (Box 24, Folder 215)
- 1973 September 14 (Box 24, Folder 216)
- 1973 November 8 (Box 24, Folder 217)
- 1974 February 14 (Box 24, Folder 218)
- 1974 May 9 (Box 24, Folder 219)
- 1974 November 21 (Box 24, Folder 220)
- 1975 February 13 (Box 24, Folder 221)
- 1975 May 8 (Box 24, Folder 222)
- 1975 November 13 (Box 24, Folder 223)
- 1976 February 12 (Box 25, Folder 224)
- 1976 May 13 (Box 25, Folder 225)
- 1976 November 18 (Box 25, Folder 226)
- 1977 February 10 (Box 25, Folder 227)
- 1977 May 12 (Box 25, Folder 228)
- 1977 November 1 (Box 25, Folder 229)
- 1978 February 9 (Box 25, Folder 230)
- 1978 May 11 (Box 25, Folder 231)
- 1978 November 9 (Box 25, Folder 232)
- 1979 February 8 (Box 25, Folder 233)
- 1979 May 10 (Box 25, Folder 234)
- 1979 November 8 (Box 25, Folder 235)
- 1980 February 14 (Box 25, Folder 236)
- 1980 May 8 (Box 26, Folder 237)
- 1980 September 25 (Box 26, Folder 238)
- 1981 May 13 (Box 26, Folder 239)
- 1981 July 7 (Box 26, Folder 240)
- 1981 November 23 (Box 26, Folder 241)
- 1982 April 13 (Box 26, Folder 242)
- 1982 November 9 (Box 26, Folder 243)
- 1983 April 12 (Box 26, Folder 244)
- 1983 July 12 (Box 26, Folder 245)
- 1983 November 8 (Box 26, Folder 246)
- 1984 November 13 (Box 27, Folder 247, Folder 248, Folder 249)
- 1985 April 19 (Box 27, Folder 251, Folder 252, Folder 250)
- 1987 July 14 (Box 28, Folder 254, Folder 253)
- 1987 November 10 (Box 28, Folder 255, Folder 256)
- 1988 April 12 (Box 28, Folder 257, Folder 258)
- 1988 July 12 (Box 28, Folder 259, Folder 260)
- 1988 November 8 (Box 28, Folder 262, Folder 261)
- 1989 April 11 (Box 29, Folder 264, Folder 263)
- 1989 July 11 (Box 29, Folder 265, Folder 266)
- 1989 November 14 (Box 30, Folder 268, Box 29, Folder 267)
- 1990 April 10 (Box 30, Folder 270, Folder 269)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1990 April 10 (Box 30, Folder 271)
- Finance Committee Meeting June 7-8, 1990 June 7-8 (Box 30, Folder 272)
- 1990 July 10 (Box 30, Folder 273, Folder 274)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1990 July 10 (Box 30, Folder 275)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1990 Sept. 10-14 (Box 30, Folder 276)
- 1990 Nov. 19 (Box 31, Folder 278, Folder 277)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1990 Dec. 13-14 (Box 31, Folder 279)
- 1991 April 2 (Box 31, Folder 280, Box 30, Folder 281)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1991 April 2 (Box 31, Folder 282)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1991 July 2-3 (Box 31, Folder 283)
- 1991 July 9 (Box 31, Folder 284, Box 32, Folder 285)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1991 July 9 (Box 32, Folder 286)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1991 Nov. 26 (Box 32, Folder 287)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1991 Dec. 13 & 16 (Box 32, Folder 288)
- 1992 April 7 (Box 32, Folder 289)
- Finance Committee's And Treasuerer's Reports, 1992 April 7 (Box 32, Folder 290)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1992 June 25-26 (Box 32, Folder 291)
- 1992 July 14 (Box 32, Folder 292)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Report, 1992 July 14 (Box 33, Folder 293)
- 1992 Nov. 10 (Box 33, Folder 294)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1992 Nov. 10 (Box 33, Folder 295)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1992 Dec. 17-18 (Box 33, Folder 296)
- 1993 April 6 (Box 33, Folder 297)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1993 April 6 (Box 33, Folder 298)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1993 June 21 (Box 33, Folder 299)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1993 July 13 (Box 33, Folder 300)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1993 Dec. 9-10 (Box 34, Folder 300)
- 1993 July 13 (Box 34, Folder 301)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1993 July 13 (Box 34, Folder 302)
- MEM, 1993 Nov. 4 (Box 34, Folder 303)
- 1993 Nov. 18 (Box 34, Folder 305, Folder 304)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1993 Nov. 18 (Box 34, Folder 306)
- 1994 April 5 (Box 35, Folder 308)
- Completed Grant Reports, 1994 April 5 (Box 35, Folder 309)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1994 April 5 (Box 35, Folder 310)
- Finance Committee Meeting, 1994 June 23-24 (Box 35, Folder 311)
- Finance Committee Meeting, June 23-24 (Box 35, Folder 312)
- 1994 July 12 (Box 35, Folder 313)
- Completed Grant Report, 1994 July 12 (Box 36, Folder 314)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1994 July 12 (Box 36, Folder 315)
- 1994 Nov. 8 (Box 36, Folder 316, Folder 317)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1994 Nov. 8 (Box 36, Folder 318)
- 1995 April 4 (Box 36, Folder 319)
- Completed Grant Reports, 1995 April 4 (Box 36, Folder 320)
- Finance Committee's and Treasurer's Reports, 1995 April 4 (Box 36, Folder 321)